<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="defaultbeans">
  <title>Default Beans</title>
 <section>
      <title>Default Beans</title>
      <para>
         Suppose you have a situation where you want to provide a default implementation of a particular service 
         and allow the user to override it as needed. Although this may sound like a job for JSR-299 alternatives, 
         they have some limitations that may make them undesirable in this situation. If we were to use an alternative
         it would require an entry in every <literal>beans.xml</literal> file in the application. This means the end 
         user may have to open up your jar file and edit the beans.xml file within, in order to override your service. 
         They will also have to do this for every bean archive in their application, and if they miss one it will 
         result in bugs. This is where default beans come in.
      </para>
      <para>
         Default beans allow you to specify a default bean for a given bean type and set of qualifiers. If no 
         bean is installed that has the same type and qualifiers then the default bean it installed. 
      </para>
      <para>
         Lets look at a real world example. Say we are writing a module to allow you to evaluate EL. If JSF 
         is available we want to use the JSF provided <literal>FunctionMapper</literal> to resolve functions in EL, 
         otherwise we just want to use a a default <literal>FunctionMapper</literal> implementation that does nothing. 
         We can achieve this as follows:
      </para>
      <programlisting role="java">
@DefaultBean(type = FunctionMapper.class)
@Mapper
public class FunctionMapperImpl extends FunctionMapper
{

   @Override
   public Method resolveFunction(String prefix, String localName)
   {
      return null;
   }

}
</programlisting>
      <para>
         And in the JSF module:
      </para>
<programlisting role="java">
public class FunctionMapperProvider
{
   @Produces
   @Mapper
   public FunctionMapper produceFunctionMapper()
   {
      return FacesContext.getCurrentInstance().getELContext().getFunctionMapper();
   }
}
</programlisting>      
   <para>
      If <literal>FunctionMapperProvider</literal> is present then it will be used by
      default, otherwise the default <literal>FunctionMapperImpl</literal> is used.
   </para>
   <warning>
      <para>
         Producer methods/fields and observer methods will not work on classes annotated <literal>@DefaultBean</literal>. 
      </para>
   </warning>
   </section>
    
</chapter>
